A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Papers 1776-1939
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Atcheson L. Hench Papers 1776-1939
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4030
This collection consists of ca. 5,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Professor Atcheson L. Hench of the University of Virginia's Department of English presented this collection to Alderman Library in 1953. The vast majority of this material represents Professor Hench's purchases from Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Wood, Charlottesville antique dealers in the 1940's and 1950's.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the correspondence, receipts, deeds, indentures and writes of various unrelated Virginia families, ca. 5,000 items, with a date range of 1776 to 1939 but with the majority of material from the years 1830 to 1890. They were collected by Atcheson L. Hench, a professor in the Department of English at the University of Virginia and a student of etymology and word usage. A few of the families and localities represented are the Davis, Henderson, Henson, Martin, Robertson and Sutherland families of Orange, Madison, Louisa, Nelson, Albemarle and Fluvanna counties.
The subjects of the correspondence are diverse, including migration westward, courting customs, education, the Civil War, and agricultural and economic conditions in Virginia, the "New South," and the West. The collection contains many deeds and receipts from the early nineteenth century and thirteen nineteenth century scrapbooks, albums, record, and cyphering books. The medical casebook of Dr. Thomas Smith, 1815- 1849, is of special note. This collection would be of interest to students of central Virginia history in particular and Southern society in general.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged alphabetically by family name. Within each family group papers were categorized as to type-correspondence, receipts, documents, or miscellaneous items-and arranged chronologically within the category.
Organization
Beathe Family Correspondence, 1857-1874 This correspondence mainly consists of the courting letters to the widowed Mrs. Beathe from Sergeant Christian Kuhl of the 31st Virginia Infantry which declare his affection and describe battles near Winchester, 1864. (ca. 39 items)
J. B. Bradford and E. C. Moore Letters, 1850-1852 The two letters of Bradford, a Virginian "fourty-niner," relates his western travels, with particular accounts of Fort Kearney, geysers, and the mining towns of California. E. C. Moore's two letters regard a gold transaction in Virginia (4 items)
Davis Family Papers, 1776-1852 Although the Davis family was clustered about Orange and Albemarle counties, this correspondence chiefly concerns commodity prices and land litigation in Kentucky, where Captain Thomas Davis had extensive holdings during the 1820's. There is some discussion of Virginia politics, with two letters of Governor James Barbour that discuss Andrew Jackson and "the Bank" being of special interest. The family documents span the years 1776-1844 and consist of deeds, land surveys, writs, a forfeiture of dowry and a few papers of the Swift Run Gap Turnpike Company, ca. 1812. (ca. 220 items)
Dempsey Family Papers, 1826-1875 Largely taken up with personal matters, the correspondence is noteworthy for several letters that describe Indiana in 1848. There are a few letters from the Civil War and a body of receipts. (ca. 70 items).
Garland Family Papers, 1815-1872 The range of topics in the Garland correspondence (1831-1869) is essentially limited to personal and family affairs with the exception of several letters from Alexander Rives that comment on the pardon of Gordon Hatcher and secession. There is a body of deeds, indentures and receipts, 1815-1872. (ca. 37 items)
Garth Family Papers, 1805-1851 Deeds, indentures and family correspondence. (ca. 22 items)
A. J. Gillespie Civil War Diary, 1862-1863 A sergeant in Pendleton's corps of artillery, Gillespie gives brief accounts of the battles of Chancellorsville and Gettysburg. (1 item)
A. B. Griffin Correspondence, 1919 A small group of letters from a rural Virginia soldier serving in the American Occupation Army of Germany, 1919. (8 items)
Hammer Family Correspondence, 1864-1865 Four letters of William and Mary Hammer, relating to the attitude and privations of a soldier in the Army of Northern Virginia during the winter of 1864-1865.
Henderson Family Papers, 1801-1833 Consisting mainly of bills and receipts, this collection of the Madison County Hendersons includes a "Proclamation to the People," 1814, a printed letter of Linn Banks, and a petition for a road, 1813.
Hiner and McLaughlin Families' Papers, 1838-1892 Many letters of these two Pocahantas County, Virginia-later, West Virginia-families are from the Civil War period and give brief accounts of cavalry skirmishes in the Valley of Virginia, Gettysburg, and Cold Harbor. There are deeds and indentures for both families, 1838-1878. (ca. 56 items)
McMaster and McVey Families' Papers, 1844-1897 Two of the subjects of this interesting series of letters are western migration to Ohio and Kansas, ca. 1858, and the conflict between pro- and anti-slavery factions in Kansas. There is a group of receipts from the later years. (ca. 70 items)
Martin Family Papers, 1776-1934 These papers consist largely of receipts, promissory notes, and business correspondence, but there are also an oath of allegiance for 1776, several eighteenth century indentures and many deeds from the early 1800's. (ca. 1500 items)
Maupin Family Correspondence, 1862-1886 Personal and family matters occupy this correspondence. (10 items)
Melton Family Correspondence, 1848-1855 These letters relate the personal and family affairs of this central Virginia family (Nelson and Buckingham Counties). (ca. 45 items)
Peake Family Correspondence, 1824-1868 The Peake family correspondence contains several letters from a family member in Illinois that briefly comment on prices and settlement and two letters from the Civil War period that describe battles in the West under generals Van Dorn and Forest. (ca. 40 items)
Robertson-Hart Family Papers, 1801-1905 This extensive and interesting correspondence spans a hundred years (1805-1905) and two generations of the Robertson family. Of note are the letters of James Hart to his daughter Fannie which describe antebellum agricultural conditions at Fruitlands Plantation, Alabama, and the courting letters of Fannie Hart and F. J. Robertson. Student life at Hampden-Sydney College and tin mining in western Virginia are among the subjects discussed in a letter group of letters by the nephews of F. J. Robertson in the 1880's. There are two sets of documents, one consisting of papers of the Virginia Tin Mining Company, another containing two professional diplomas and a surgeon's comission, C. S. A. (ca. 850 items)
Rogers Family Correspondence, 1835-1852 The letters that describe California society in the 1840's highlight this personal and family correspondence.
Hench Correspondence Regarding Thomas Smith, 1940 and William Smith Letter, 1854 After acquiring Dr. Thomas Smith's notebook, Professor Hench wrote the Universities of Maryland and Pennsylvania to obtain more information on Dr. Smith. The letter from Pennsylvania relates that a Thomas Smith of Fauquier County matriculated in 1843-1844. Also included among this correspondence is a letter to "Dr. Thomas" from a William Smith, travelling in New York in 1854. One of the most interesting items in the entire collection, this letter describes the city and harbor, discusses the respective merits of Southern and Northern society, abolition, and the political future. (4 items)
Sutherland Family Correspondence, 1855-1892 Many of the letters that comprise this large correspondence are from the Civil War period. James Sutherland was in the 44th Virginia Infantry, his brother Dumfreys served with the cavalry and in the exchange of letters with their sister Jane, mention is made of economic conditions in Palmyra, the defense of Richmond, local magisterial elections, and the draft. (ca. 150 items)
Cameron Waddell Correspondence, 1866-1875 In this courting letters, Mr. Waddell describes his legal studies and career as an agricultural machinery salesman in North Carolina. (12 items)
Wood Family Papers, 1827-1909 This collection is made up largely of the receipts of John H. Wood of Albemarle County. There is a small group of business letters and papers, the latter including an abstract of the duties of the Surveyor of Roads, 1868, and many writs. (ca. 500 items)
Miscellaneous Civil War Correspondence Allen, Brown, Burrer, Estes, Gilbert, Roudabush, and Thomas are the names of the correspondents comprising this group of unrelated letters which generally narrate camp life and the soldiers' attitudes. Of note is a Confederate "tax in kind" return of N. W. Berkeley, 1864; and a letter of March 28, 1863. (ca. 40 items)
Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1859-1912 Letters of John Armstrong, N. W. Bradley, George Clarke, John Mesh, John West and others. (ca. 45 items)
Miscellaneous Items from the Saunders(?) Blacksmith Account Book, ca. 1855-1870 and n.d. Advertisements, newspaper clippings, and recipes. (ca. 25 items)
Contents List
- Correspondence of the Beathe Family 1857-1874 (Box 1)
- Letters of J. B. Bradford and E. C. Moore 1850-1852 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Davis Family 1798-1838 (Box 1)
  (2 folders)
- Correspondence of the Davis Family 1841-1852 and n.d. (Box 1)
- Davis Family: Speech n.d. (Box 1)
- Legal Documents of the Davis Family: Deeds, writs, etc. 1776-1844 (Box 1)
- Ledger and Accounts of the Davis Family 1800-1845 (Box 1)
- Receipts and Bills of the Davis Family 1791-1829 (Box 1)
- Receipts and Bills of the Davis Family 1830-1852 (Box 2)
- Davis Family Miscellaneous Items: Confederate Almanac, newspaper clippings, stud poster, etc. n.d. (Box 2)
- Receipts and Miscellaneous Items of the Dempsey Family 1834-1874 and n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Garland Family 1831-1869 (Box 2)
- Papers of the Garland Family: Deeds, Receipts and Miscellaneous Items 1815-1872 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Garth Family 1819-1851 (Box 2)
- Legal Documents of the Garth Family: Deeds, Indentures and writs 1805-1850 (Box 2)
- A. J. Gillespie's Civil War Diary 1862-1863 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Hammer Family 1864-1865 (Box 2)
- Henderson Family Papers: Proclamations re: War of 1812, distlling licenses, etc. ca. 1813-1814 and n.d. (Box 2)
- Receipts and Bills of the Henderson Family 1801-1833 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Henson Family 1859-1906 and n.d. (Box 3)
  (3 folders)
- Correspondence of the Hiner and McLaughlin Families 1859-1892 and n.d. (Box 3)
- Legal Documents: Deeds and Indentures of the Hiner and McLaughlin Families 1838-1878 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of the McMaster and McVey Families 1844-1897 (Box 3)
- McVey Family Bills, Receipts, and Business Correspondence, Miscellaneous Items, and a "First Reader" ca. 1880-1890 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of the Martin Family 1830-1934 (Box 4)
- Legal Documents of the Martin Family: Contracts, Deeds, Indentures, etc. ca. 1776-1910 (Box 4)
- Ledger and Account Sheets of the Martin Family ca. 1755-1900 (Box 4)
- Receipts and Bills of the Martin Family ca. 1769-1829 (Box 4)
- Receipts and Bills of the Martin Family 1830-1939 and n.d. (Box 5)
  (4 folders)
- Martin Family Miscellaneous Items n.d. (Box 6)
- Correspondence of the Maupin Family 1862-1886 (Box 6)
- Correspondence of the Melton Family 1848-1885 and n.d. (Box 6)
- Correspondence of the Peake Family 1824-1868 (Box 6)
- Correspondence of the Robertson and Hart Families 1805-1885 (Box 6)
- Correspondence of the Robertson and Hart Families 1886-1905 and n.d. (Box 7)
- Professional Diplomas of the Robertson and Hart Families ca. 1851-1861 (Box 7)
- Robertson and Hart Papers re: Virginia Tin Mining Company 1879-1899 (Box 7)
- Robertson and Hart Miscellaneous Items ca. 1880 and n.d. (Box 7)
- Correspondence of the Rogers Family 1835-1852 (Box 7)
- Hench Correspondence re: Notebook of Thomas W. Smith and letter of William Smith 1854, 1940 (Box 7)
- Correspondence of the Sutherland Family 1855-1893 and n.d. (Box 7)
- Correspondence of D. Cameron Waddell 1866-1875 (Box 7)
- Correspondence of the Wood Family 1869-1906 (Box 8)
- Papers of John Wood 1845-1906 (Box 8)
- Receipts and Bills of John Wood 1827-1885 (Box 8)
- Wood Family Receipts and Bills 1886-1906 (Box 8)
- Wood Family Miscellaneous Items n.d. (Box 9)
- Civil War Correspondence 1861-1865 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1859-1912 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Material from the Saunders(?) Blacksmith Account Book ca. 1855-1870 and n.d. (Box 9)
- Cyphering Book of Achilles and Norman Barksdale, consisting of mathematical and surveying problems ca. 1814-1830 (Box 9)
- Commonplace Book of a Miss Barclay, [Bedford, Pennsylvania] ca. 1830-1834 (Box 10)
- Account Book of B. K. Wood of Albemarle County ca. 1836-1851 (Box 10)
- Account Book of the Executors of Abram Gaar 1852-1860 (Box 10)
- Scrapbook of Thomas Harm and/or Robert Nelson ca. 1840-1870 (Box 10)
- Robert D. Dempsey - New Testament ca. 1863-1865 (Box 11)
- Account and Scrapbook of William Russell of Winchester, Virginia ca. 1856 (Box 11)
- Commonplace Book of Mary Eppes Thweatt, wife of Rev. P. F. Berkeley of Amelia County, Virginia ca. 1830-1833 (Box 11)
- Commonplace Book of Helen Stephens 1862-1886 (Box 11)
- Blacksmith's Account Book of Thomas [Saunders?] ca. 1855-1870 (Box 11)
- Dr. Thomas Smith, Medicine Casebook and Notebook with a record of patients and their treatment ca. 1815-1849 (Box 11)